<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A solemn warning to all members of this kirk from the Commission of the Generall Assemblie with an act for censuring such as act or comply with the sectarian armie now infesting this kingdom.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35590</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15479745</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15479745</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1148:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A solemn warning to all members of this kirk from the Commission of the Generall Assemblie with an act for censuring such as act or comply with the sectarian armie now infesting this kingdom.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
                  <author>Ker, A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by James Brown ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: A. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103550:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103550:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SOLEMN WARNING To all the Members of this Kirk, FROM The Commiſsion of the <hi>Generall Aſſemblie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH</hi> An Act, for cenſuring ſuch as act, or comply with the Sectarian Armie, <hi>Now infesting this Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ABERDENE.</hi> Imprinted by James Brown, ANNO 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:103550:2"/>
            <head>PERTH, 7. Januar. 1651.</head>
            <p>THE COMMISSION of the GENERALL ASSEMBLIE, Seriouſly conſidering the preſent Diſtreſs and Danger of the LORDS PEOPLE in this KIRK and KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM, through the Unjuſt Violence and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, and the Pernicious Errours of the Sectarian Armie of ENGLAND, continuing now a long tyme in this LAND; Haue found it neceſſarie to emit this SOLEMN WAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING, for Information of all the Members of this KIRK, and ſtirring them up to their duetie at this tyme: AND, Do Ordayn the ſame, To bee Publictlie read in all the CONGREGATIONS of this KIRK; Whereof PRESBYTERIES are to take eſpeciall care, And to make report.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103550:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Perth,</hi> 
                  <date>7. <hi>Januar.</hi> 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>A Solemn Warning, to all the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Kirk, From the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> of the General Aſſembly.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it hath pleaſed the LORD, who is wonderfull in counſell, and excellent in working, in the carrying on of His Work, ſince the tyme of the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving of our Nationall Covenant, for the Mayntenance of that Work in this Kirk and Kingdom, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Solemn League and Covenant, with our neyg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bour Kingdoms of England and Ireland, for propagating and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſame amongſt them, to exerciſe His people with many tryalls: So it hath been His great Mercie, not only to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſerue the publick judicatories of this Kirk faythfull and ſteadfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with him in his Covenant and Cauſe: But alſo to furniſh them with Wiſdom and Cowrage, to diſcern and giue ſeaſonable Warnings agaynſt diverſe Tentations and Snares of the tymes, and to hold foorth to the people of GOD their dueties in every tryall; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it hath come to paſs, through the LORDS Bleſſing vpon their labours, that ſuch as feared GOD, have been much helped to ſtand faſt in the Cauſe of GOD, in the ſaddeſt hours, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Tentations, vntill the LORD did make a way to eſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:103550:3"/>And now, the LORD in His Wyſe and Moſt Holy Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having brought His People of this Land, unto as ſad a tryall, as any that ever wee haue been in ſince the beginning of the Work, by the Invaſion, Prevalencie, and Oppreſſion of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarian Partie of England; Although at the tyme of their firſt Invading of this Kingdom, the Injuſtice and Perfidiouſneſs of their Cauſe, was aboundantly diſcovered by the Committee of Eſtates, and the Generall Aſſemblie, and Seaſonable Warning was given agaynſt complyance with them, (which wee hope all who truely loue GOD, Religion, and Governement, have not yet forgotten and caſten behind their back, But will make conſcience to follow) Yet, conſidering that the LORD for our tryall hath ſuffered the Tentation to grow, and perceaving that ſome alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die perfidiouſlie and unnaturallie haue gone in to them; Wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring to bee faythfull to GOD in our Station, fynd it a duetie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cumbent to vs, to renew the Word of Exhortation to all the people of GOD in this Land; hoping that the LORD accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to His wonted way of Bleſſing the Word of His Servants, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l not let it be ineffectuall upon the heartes of ſuch as feare HIM.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, therefore, Wee exhort, and as the Servants and Meſſengers of IESUS CHRIST, Do in His Name, charge the People of GOD in this Kirk and Kingdom, To avoyd all ſors of Complying with theſe foreſayd Enemies; Whether by ſpeaking favourablie of them, and their wayes, or ſpeaking diſreſpectfullie of the publick, juſt, and neceſſarie Reſolutions and Proceedings of Kirk and State, for oppoſing their wicked Deſigns, agaynſt this Kingdom, and delyvering the Land from their Unjuſt and Cruell Oppreſſion, or reproaching ſuch in Kirk and ſtate, as have been conſtant in the COVENANT and CAUSE of GOD, and adhered to our firſt Principles, with Imputations and Aſperſions of Malignancie, and Back-ſlyding, becauſe of their Zeale againſt that Enemie, and care to haue the Liberties &amp; Government of this Kingdom mayntayned agaynſt their Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or by Converſing with them familiarlie, or by Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any thing in an actiue way, for their mayntenance and help:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103550:3"/>But eſpeciallie, by keeping correſpondence with them me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatelie, or immediatelie, to giue them intelligence of the Counſells, Reſolutions, and Proceedings of Kirk or State, by going in vnto, or joyning with them in Counſell or Armes, or anie other way of acting for their Cauſe, or ſeducing others to anie of theſe: And to the effect, that all may bee the more ſtirred vp to guard themſelves agaynſt their fayr and entyſing words, and agaynſt the ſuggeſtions and inſinuations of anie that are Agents for them, Wee deſyre and warn all People of the Land, to take notice of, and conſider, beſyde ſuch things as haue been repreſented in former Papers:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That as they did moſt Unjuſtly and Perfidiouſly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade this KINGDOM, contrary to Covenant and Treaties, as was cleared before the world, by the Papers emitted both by Kirk and State, at their firſt incomming, the intentions of this kingdom, as then, ſo now, being no other, but the mayntenance of Religion, their own juſt Rights, Liberties, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not owning any Malignant intereſt, nor owning any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt what-ſo-ever of mans, But according to the COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANT, in ſubordination to Religion, and the ſaferie of theſe Kingdoms; So that as their Invaſion was moſt Unjuſt and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious, So is their guiltineſs now exceeding much increaſſed, and heightned, by much innocent Blood-ſhed of the People &amp; Saincts of GOD in this LAND, the more than Barbarous uſage of our Priſoners, by ſterving many hundreths of them, with Hunger and Cold, and ſending away many others, as Slaves vnto remote parts of the world; by laying many Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Land waſte, chaſing Miniſters from their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Spoyling, Plundering, and Oppreſſing the People of GOD in the Land.</p>
            <p>Now, For any of this Kirk and Kingdom, to comply and joyn with this Enemie, and to act any wayes for them, were it not beſydes the unnaturall Treacherie of it, agaynſt their Native Countrey (a Villanie which hath been abhominable and execrable, even amongſt all Heathen Nations, much more amongſt Chriſtian People) Were it not a moſt manifeſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103550:4"/>and formall Violating of our Solemn Covenant, where in wee are bound to mayntayn Religion, the Liberties, and Governement of the Kingdom, the Kings Majeſties Perſon, and Government, in the defence of Religion, and everie one another in this Common Cauſe? And, alſo, To bee acceſſorie vnto, and bring vpon themſelves the guiltineſs of all theſe mens oppoſition to the Work of GOD, uſurpation, perſecution of faythfull and ſtedfaſt COVENANTERS in the other two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and of their Unjuſt Invading of this Kingdom, all the Blood-ſhed, Deſpyte agaynſt the Ordinances of GOD, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Oppreſſion, and Villanies, which they have done ſince they came into it: And would it not, not only render vs vyle and reproachfull to all Nations round about vs; But alſo draw on the Wrath of GOD, Who is a Severe Avenger of the breach of COVENANTS made in His Name; though they bee but with men? Verilie, our hearts do tremble to think, and all People in this Land, haue cauſe to mourn before the LORD, that any haue been found among<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t vs, who haue alreadie fallen into ſuch abhominable and fearfull defection, contrarie to ſo So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Vowes, Eſpecially having ſo clear and wel grounded Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies and Warnings tymouſly given them, both by State and Kirk, to avoyd ſuch Courſes. Theſe that hitherto haue been preſerved from ſuch falling, would be the more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full over their hearts, and take heed, leſt they fall, and be not high mynded, but fear. Wee do not think it neceſſary to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in guarding the mynds of People agaynſt the Snare of that Argument, Which the Enemies take from the great ſucceſs, and ſeries of providences, wherewith their undertakings and courſe have been followed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereby they would dazle the eyes of the Ignorant and Simple, this being aboundantlie da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in former Papers, and even of it ſelf evidently abſurd, the Word of GOD being ſo clear for this, and experiences in all Generations yeelding ſo manyfold examples thereof, That often tymes in the LORDS Holy Providence; wicked men, in moſt wicked courſes; even agaynſt GODS own People, may haue much proſperitie, for a tyme, for the tryall and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103550:4"/>of his own, and the greater judgement vpon their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, when they haue filled vp the meaſure of their iniquitie. Providences are not our Rules, whereby to judge of the juſtice, or injuſtice of a courſe, But the Law and the Teſtimonie, if they ſpeak not according to this Word, there is no light in them, what-ſo-ever bee the ſucceſſes of men; But wee ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort every one, and it will bee their wiſdom, to watch agaynſt and to hee aware of the Snares of ſuch, as by ſubtile ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and whiſperings, labour to alienate the hearts and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of People from theſe that are in publick truſt in State and Kirk, and to render all their Reſolutions for the publick ſafetie ſuſpitious and odious, the hearkening where unto, is indeed a ſtep vnto Defection, and may readily leade on to down right complyance with the Enemie.</p>
            <p>In the next place; Wee earneſtly deſyre all People to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That it is not enough for them in theſe tymes, Not to joyne or act with, or for theſe Enemies; But that they ought alſo according to the utter moſt of their power, to act, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them ſelves agaynſt them: And, therefore, wee do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort every one, in the Fear of GOD, to giue all loyall and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie obedience, unto ſuch neceſſary and lawfull Orders, and Commands, as are, or ſhall be emitted by the Civill Authoritie, in reference to acting agaynſt the ſayd Enemie. If ever there was People in the world, who had cauſe to bee a willing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to this, and to beſtir them ſelves, with all their power, to oppoſe, and defend them ſelves, agaynſt an Enemie, Wee cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynlie, the People of this Land, at this day, haue cauſe to do ſo, agaynſt this preſent Enemie; Whether wee conſider the Enemies what they are, and what is the cauſe of their Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and Perſecuting vs; Or whether wee conſider our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, that are in hazard of their Deſigns, and Crueltie; Or whether wee conſider the Bands and Obligations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are tyed before GOD, and the World, to mayntayn and defend the ſame.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, Wee ſhall not need to adde any new thing to that which was holden foorth by the COMMITTIE of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103550:5"/>ESSTATES in their anſwer to the declaration of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Parliament of England, and the declaration of that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, when they firſt entred into this Land, we ſhall only deſire that what was ſaid there, may be now called to minde, and reviewed, Pag. 17.18.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, we ſhall deſire all ingenuous, honeſt, and godlie hearts, to conſider theſe things, 1, How many of our deare brethren, fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone, are ſlain with the ſword, innocentlie, and without cauſe, and how manie carried into Captivitie, and therein ſterved with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or cold, &amp; ſent away as ſlaves. 2. A great part of our Land ſubdued, and lying under their feete, and the LORDS peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple our brethren there, oppreſſed, ſpoyled, inſlaved in their bodies, endangered in their ſoules, which lye open to the poyſon of their pernicious errours, being deſtitute of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of GOD, and their Miniſters, who might informe, comfort, and ſtrengthen their hearts in the LORD, whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed condition, and ſadd afflictions, crye to us for help and relieff, and crye to Heaven agaynſt us, if we ſhall lye by, for that woe, which is pronounced agaynſt theſe that are at caſe in SION, and remember not the affliction of Ioſeph. 3. What theſe are alreadie ſuffering, that the ſame is threatned agaynſt the reſt of the Land, and cannot be avoyded, if we ſhall not tymouſlie ryſe up, and ſeeking the LORDS help and aſſiſtance, faythfullie and actively make uſe of that power (which GOD hath mercifully in His providence left yet in our hand) agaynſt their violence. 4. Is anie thing leſſe intended, and perſued by theſe men, then the deſtruction of our King, now in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with GOD and his people, the utter overturning of our governement, under which we have lived, &amp; ſubſiſted for ſo many generations, and the enthralling us and this ancient Kingdom in bondage and ſlaverie unto them, as without all which, they conceive they cannot promiſe ſecuritie to them ſelves in their violent and wicked unparallelled uſurpations at home in their native countrey? 5. Is not Religion alſo, and the cauſe of IESUS CHRIST (which ought to be deare and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103550:5"/>more precious unto us, nor any thing or intereſt worldlie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven, and for defence of which our lyves ought not to be deare to us) in danger of utter ſubverſion and ruine, by theſe mens crueltie, and impietie? What they have done in their owne countrey, in the matters of Religion, by continuall obſtructing the work of reformation, by crafetie under my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, whill it was carrying on, and then at laſt, breaking it in peices, when they had gotten power in their hands, by avowing all ſorts of impious and blaſphemous errours, and ſetting up ane abhominable toleration thereof, and now at laſt of poperie; by oppreſſing, perſecuteing, and caſting out ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and faithfull Miniſters of CHRIST, for preaching, and ſpeaking againſt their errours, injuſtice, and uſurpation, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to approve their uſurped power, Is now ſo manifeſt befor the world, that none can be ignorant thereof. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in their invadeing of us, they pretend only to be acting civill matters, as they ſay, their libertie &amp; ſafetie, yet certainely, becauſe they cannot promiſe themſelfs ſecuritie in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, confuſions, and impieties in England, ſo long as Religion ſtands inteer in this kingdome, eſpeciallie ſo long as presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall governement, which is the hedge of trueth, and a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to hereſies, and Hereticks, is keiped up, and our religious League and Covenant, which binds to the maintainance of Religion, is avowed by any of theſe nations, their crueltie and violence will have no reſt, if they gett way, untill they have over-whelmed us with the ſame confuſions in Religion, which they have effectuated on the neighbour kingdome, and when Religion is overthrowne, and deſtroyed, theſe kingdomes (which GOD avert, and we hope he ſhall, for his own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Names ſake) is it not endangered in all Orthodox proteſtant kirks abroad round about us? Who this day are looking at the ſtanding or falling of it in theſe kingdomes, as the apparent means of the ſtanding or falling of it amongſt themſelfs alſo. By this brief narration, may be ſeen, that which we doubt not but every ſenſible man doeth ſee by him ſelf; That what ſo ever can be deare and precious to any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103550:6"/>in the world, are all to us now lying at the ſtake, and that therefore every one amongſt us, as we would not render our ſelves reproachfull to all nations round about us, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie involve our ſelves in the greateſt miſeries that a people can be brought unto, ought to take their lyfe in their hand, and according to their ſtations, places, and power, to be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming to the defence of theſe things againſt vnjuſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p>And now in the third place, Let every one of us adde to theſe things, the conſideration of the bonds and obligations, that lye vpon us to this duetie, by the Law of GOD, the law of nature, our Nationall Covenant, and Solemne League and Covenant, and the paines therein contained, whereunto we have devoted our ſelves, if we ſhall deſert, or faill in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that duetie, and we think every ſenſible heart may tremble to intertayne any thought of lying back from, or ſlacking in the duetie, being called thereunto by lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</p>
            <p>We doubt not but ſundrie things may be, and are alreadie ſuggeſted to the people of GOD in this Land, to weaken their hands, and to diſcowrage their hearts, in doing their duetie, and to obſtruct neceſſary raiſing and levying of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at this tyme, againſt which we-deſyre all, in the feare of GOD, to arme and guarde them ſelves, that they hearken not thereunto, as they would not bring upon them ſelves the guilt of al that the Land hath already ſuffered, &amp; all that it may yet ſuffer, in Religion, Liberties, Governement, the lyves and eſtates of people, from that enemie, if they be not with-ſtood. Certainlie we know nothing which ought to move any to lye back, or to ſlacken their hands in any wyſe.</p>
            <p>As to what is ſuggeſted by ſome, for treating with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, rather than hazard the effuſion of more blood, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that blood, eſpecially the blood of GODS People, ſhould be very precious, and rather than the effuſion of it be hazarded, very much damnage in our matters, ſhould be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained, and borne with, yea much in outward things quitt and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103550:6"/>renounced; And we confeſſe that we ſhould ſeeke peace with all men, as farre as is poſſible, and follow after it, And if there might be a Treatie with theſe enemies, even after all the wrongs they have done in this Land, without wronging Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in theſe kingdomes, united in Covenant, for mutuall defence, and maintainance of Religion, without making our ſelves acceſſorie to all the violence done by them againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Governement, in England, without falſifying our vowes made to GOD, our Declarations and Treaties, made and emitted before the world, to maintain the Kings perſon, juſt right, and authoritie, by all lawfull and neceſſarie means, according to the Covenant. In a word, without quyting the Covenant, and running into the ſame guiltineſſe of perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and perjurie, that they haue runne into, we ſhould not be againſt it, but we leave it unto all honeſt and judicious hearts to think if that can be.</p>
            <p>But the maine and principall thing, which we perceave may be repreſented vnto, and may breed ſcruple in the myndes of honeſt people in the Land, as to acting at this tyme, in the way and courſe agreed upon, and appointed in the publict re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, is, Becauſe of the admiſſion of ſuch to act againſt the enemie, as have been formerlie excluded; For removing this ſcruple from the myndes of theſe that are honeſt and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie (who we acknowledge ought to be had in tender reſpect) we doe deſyre, firſt, That the courſe reſolved upon, and the neceſſitie requyring the ſame, may be looked upon, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie conſidered, The reſolution is this, That all ſenſible perſons be raiſed, and permitted to act againſt the publict ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, for defence of the kingdome, excepting ſuch as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, or forefaulted, or knowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e profane, and flagitious, or have been from the beginning, or continue ſtill, or are at this preſent tyme obſtinate enemies to the Cauſe and Covenant; And provyding that no perſon get ſuch power put into their hands, as may be prejudiciall to the Cauſe of GOD: The neceſſitie of this courſe is ſo great and evident, that no man can but ſee it, Conſidering the neceſſarie duetie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103550:7"/>of juſt defence, againſt an enemie intending by violence to deſtroy our Liberties and Governement, and to force us to quyte and renounce our Covenant, ſworne to the moſt High GOD; And conſidering, That our former forces being rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a great part of the kingdome being abſolutelie under the power of the enemie, It is not poſſible to rayſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent power, in warrantable prudence, to oppoſe the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, unleſſe there by a more generall calling footth of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in parts that are yet free, then have been before. Now the caſe being thus, can the calling of ſuch as are ſubjects of the kingdome, limited with ſuch exceptions, and proviſions, be a ſinfull courſe, or ſould any truelie godlie and honeſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, withdraw their neceſſarie concurrence, for the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the kingdome.</p>
            <p>For firſt, It hath been through all generations, and is the univerſall, uncontroverted practiſe of all Chriſtian king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and States, approved by the judgement of the ſoundeſt Proteſtant Divynes, in caſe of juſt and neceſſarie defence, againſt forraigne invaſion, to imploy all ſuch as are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged ſubjects and citizens, in ſuch a way as is not evidentlie deſtructive to Religion, and particularlie the practiſe of our owne firſt reformers of this Kirk, who did receive and admitt unto communion of Counſells, and acting againſt the Queene Regent, and her faction of Frenches, and others, ſundrie of the ſubjects, who had been before upon her part, oppoſing the Profeſſours of the true Religion, then called the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, when as they came to acknowledge the errour of their former courſe, and were willing to joyne with the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Cauſe of GOD.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, As the law of nature doeth bynd and obliedge every one, that is a member of the politick bodie of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or State, to endevour to the uttermoſt of their power, the preſervation of the whole, and of the fellow members, in a juſt quarrell and cauſe, againſt unjuſt violence, which if they refuſe to doe, they are guiltie of murther, and treacherie agaynſt the Common-wealth: So this ſame law of nature al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103550:7"/>the bodie, and layeth an obligation upon ſuch as are Rulers, to call for the help and aſſiſtance of every member, as neceſſitie requyreth, for defence and delyverance of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, from deſtruction (provyding it may be without the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of a greater good, than is the preſervation of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, as it is in the preſent caſe and publict reſolution) which if they refuſe, or neglect to doe, they runne them ſelves into the ſame guiltineſſe, and betray their truſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, The Word of GOD doeth hold out to us ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cleare warrand for this practiſe: We may fynd in the book of Iudges, That, when upon defection from the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Religion, and the Covenant of GOD, that ancient Kirk was brought under the oppreſſion of forraigne enemies, yet ſo ſoone as the LORD, of His good pleaſure, raiſed up Governours, for their defence and delyverance, the whole people were raiſed, and gathered together for that end, and called out promiſcuouſlie, not-with-ſtanding a great part of them, no queſtion, had been in the defection, and it cannot be ſayd, without groundleſſe raſhneſſe, that all ſuch had given convincing evidences of their repentance, nor do we fynd that any godly refuſed to concurre with their fellow ſubjects, or that any of their Governours are reproved for not excluding from ryſing in armes, for the neceſſarie defence, and delyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Land, ſuch as had been in the defection: But on the contrarie, we ſynd ſuch ſadlie reproved, and terrible cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes pronounced againſt them, who came not foorth to joyne in the worke, See Iud: 5. verſ. 15.16.17. and 23.2. The lyke may be ſeen in the Hiſtorie of the Kings, and Chronicles, where after defection from Religion, and the Covenant of GOD, gracious reforming kings aroſe, and had to doe againſt forraigne invaſion. 3. We doe fynd in 1. Sam. 11. a cleare exemple of this practiſe, approven of GOD, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with His Bleſſing, making it ſuccesfull, where Saul, in the caſe of Iabeſh Gilead, beſieged by a forraigne enemie, commandeth all Iſrael to come foorth, for the deſence and delyverie of their brethren, vnder the paine of ſevere civill
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103550:8"/>cenſure, and accordinglie, all being moved by the feare of GOD, falling vpon them, as it is ſayd, They did come foorth, as one man; yet as we may perceive Cap. 10. verſ. ultim. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them (as is apparent a great faction) were ſonnes of Beliall, wicked and turbulent perſons, who as they had before turbulentlie rejected Samuels governement, and requyred a king; ſo then had they oppoſed the Word, and cleare revealed will of GOD, in calling Saul to the government of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Neither is there any thing can be brought in Scripture, which ſpeaketh againſt this reſolution in our preſent caſe, to wit, Of juſt and neceſſarie defence, againſt forraigne inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereby the whole Kingdome, Lyves, Liberties, and eſtates of the people thereof are in danger of utter ruine.</p>
            <p>As for any ſcruple or doubt, which may be in the mynds of honeſt and godlie people, agaynſt the publict reſolution, there may be cleare and ſufficient ſatisfaction unto ſuch as are not wilfullie reſolved unto the contrarie: For, as to former declarations and publict reſolutions, and our ſolemne acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement and engagement, made after the unlawfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt England, whereby manie are debarred from places of power, and truſt, in counſells and armies, It would be conſidered, that theſe things were done in relation to acting in a way of proſecution of the cauſe; but were no wayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the prejudice of juſt and neceſſarie defence of the kingdome againſt forraigne invaſion, for which we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and bound by the law of nature (which no humane lawes or reſolutions can infringe or prejudge) to make uſe of all ſubjects in the kingdome, if the making uſe of them be not ſinfull in it ſelfe. And to the end it may appeare unto all who are ſcrupled from the ſolemn engagement concerning the preſent publict reſolution for acting againſt the enemie, That the intention and end of that engagement was no other then what hath been preſently ſayd, we doe deſyre it may be remembred that at the tyme when that ſolemne acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and engagement was a forming and drawing up, it was repreſented by ſome then preſent that it might be a thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103550:8"/>to the kingdomes ſafetie incaſe of forraigne inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if ſo many were abſolutely debarred from taking armes. And it was then anſwered publicklie, that in ſuch a caſe, all ſubjects within the kingdome, might and ought to ryſe for the juſt defence thereof: And therefore in the obligatorie part of the acknowledgement and engagement in the 6. article there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, pag. 12. which concernerh complying with malignants, nothing is expreſſed which importeth the bynding up of the hands of the kingdom from imploying any that are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged ſubjects for the neceſſarie defence thereof, nor is there ſo much as any mention of ARMIES made therein at all. Theſe things are well knowne, and cannot be forgotten by ſuch as were upon the Commiſſion at that tyme. As for anie thing that is ſayd in latter declarations, concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, even in relation to defence againſt our invaders, as it ſtretcheth further then the known intentions of our firſt reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions; So it is to be conſidered, that it was in a tyme when the whole kingdome was inteere, and their might be choyſe made of inſtruments to act, we confeſſe that in ſuch a caſe choyſe ſhould be made of the beſt inſtruments; But the caſe is altered, and yet, neither at this tyme, is it reſolved that any ſhall be imployed, that are profane or continuing in enmitie to the Covenant or cauſe of GOD. As to what is alleadged from the eminent danger, apprehended to follow upon, and accompanie the way reſolved vpon, becauſe, thereby manie being to be imployed, who have formerlie been in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and courſes prejudiciall to the cauſe, It may be feared, that theſe having gotten power in their hands, cannot but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the ſame according to their owne principles, and for eſtabliſhing their owne ends, deſtructive to the Work of GOD, In anſwer to this, We deſyre it be conſidered: 1. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there were ſome danger in this kynd, yet it is not certaine and inevitable; And on the other hand, if neceſſary help, in it ſelfe not ſinfull, be not employed, there is certaine ruine, from the wickedneſſe and crueltie of our enemies, both to kingdom and cauſe, without an extraordinarie divine work, which we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103550:9"/>have no warrand to look for, neglecting ordinarie meanes. 2. Many of theſe who have been debarred hitherto, have been formerlie active and forward for the Covenant and Cauſe of GOD, have now ackowledged the ſinfulneſſe of their fal from their ſteadfaſtneſſe, &amp; have bound them ſelves to ſteadfaſtneſſe &amp; faythfulneſſe in tyme coming, by all the bonds that can be impoſed upon men. 3. The reaſon why many of theſe did oppoſe the Cauſe of GOD, was their ſinfull prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Kings intereſt, which was then in oppoſition to the Cauſe; But now, that being removed, and the Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and the Cauſe of GOD being joyned, there is not ſuch danger that way.</p>
            <p>We acknowledge, that it is all one with GOD, to ſave with many, or with few, and that, as it is a great provocation to put truſt and confidence in multitudes, or in the ſtrength of meanes, ſo alſo it is a great ſinne to be misbelieving, when GOD in His Providence redacteth us to ſcarcetie of ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie meanes; yet this is no ground for us to neglect the uſe of lawfull, neceſſarie, and competent meanes, when GOD doeth afford them, ſuch as He hath left, bleſſed be His Name, to us in this Land yet in ſome meaſure; But how a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meanes can be had, no man of underſtanding can ſee, without ſuch a calling foorth of the people in theſe parts of the Land that are yet free from the oppreſſion of the enemie, as is held foorth in the publick reſolution, which courſe being not ſinfull in it ſelfe, and being neceſſarie in the preſent caſe and condition of the kingdome, if anie ſhall ſtumble thereat, the ſcandal is not GIVEN, but taken; And if they doe refuſe to concurre therein, according to the duetie whereunto they are bound, by the law of nature, and the Covenant, they cannot but highlie ſinne agaynſt GOD; Yea, ſuppoſe the civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhould imploy ſome inſtruments for defence of the Land, whom they ought not to employ (which we hope they will not doe, and if they ſhould, we would not fayle to teſtifie agaynſt them) yet this will be no juſt ground, nor give warrand to any godly in the Land, to deſert, or lye back from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103550:9"/>performance of that neceſſarie duetie, which they owe to their native countrey, in a juſt cauſe, but their part were to goe about this with all diligence, mourning for the ſinne of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Therefore, we doe againe in the Name of the LORD, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and exhort all the people of GOD in this Kirk and kingdome, that in obedience to the lawfull command of Civill Authoritie, they ſhall readilie, honeſtlie, and chearfullie, goe about all the dueties, that relate to our owne juſt defence, That none, in ſuch an exigent, either through baſe mynding their owne eaſe, and perſonall ſafetie, more than the publick ſafetie of the Land, and Cauſe of GOD, lye aback, or by the ſuggeſtions or whiſperings of any, ſlandering the publick reſolution of Kirk and State, obſtruct, or retarde the preſent neceſſarie Levies, for the Defence of the kingdome, and Cauſe, or ſuffer them ſelves to be hindered from their duetie; But that everie one in his ſtation, lay out him ſelfe to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and neither ſpare his perſon, nor paines, nor meanes, for the acquyting of him ſelfe, and encowraging of others. Our cauſe is righteous, what-ſo-ever it hath pleaſed the LORD in His Holie, Iuſt, and Wyſe Providence, to bring upon us, for our ſinnes agaynſt His MAJESTIE, eſpeciallie our great miſpryſing, and contempt of the glorious Goſpell, and of His Sonne IESUS CHRIST. We ſtand for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Religion, Lyves, Liberties, Families, Eſtates, Countrey, Governement, our lawfull King, and his juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in the Defence of Religion, and everie thing that is or can be deare vnto anie people, all which are in hazard to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and ruined by our wicked and perfidious enemies, if ſo be we ſhall not in the LORDS Strength activelie beſtirre our ſelves, for our juſt Defence. And now alſo the ſadd and deſolate condition of the Citie of our ſolemnities, and the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of all our deare Brethren, under the feete of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, cry alowd to us, who are bound by nature, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to account the injuries done to them, as if they were done to our ſelves; who knoweth but the LORD who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103550:10"/>hath not gone out with our Armies agaynſt this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, will now returne, and haue mercie on His people, and ſhow foorth His diſpleaſure agaynſt theſe who are helping forward the affliction? Certaynlie the meaſure of their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is filling up, and their feete ſhall ſlyde in due tyme, for the day of vengeance is in the LORDS heart, and the yeare of recompenſe for Zions contraverſie, He will not alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, nor be angrie for ever with His people, nor ſuffer the rod of the wicked to reſt upon their lot, leſt they put foorth their hands to wickedneſſe. Let us aryſe, and doe our due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, truſting IN HIS NAME, and believing the words of His Prophets; And that our ſinnes may not ſtand up to ſeparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, and our GOD, let all of us, King, Nobles, Paſtours, and people of all rankes, labour more ſeriouſlie, and ſincerelie, to ſearch out our provocations agaynſt GOD, and to be more deeplie humbled for the ſame, to apply the LORD IESUS by fayth, for our peace and reconciliation with GOD, and to powre out our ſoules before Him, that He may haue mercie vpon us through IESUS CHRIST. and ſave us for His owne Names ſake. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act">
            <opener>
               <dateline>Perth, <date>14 December, 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>Act for cenſuring ſuch as act, or comply, with the Sectarian Armie, <hi>now infesting this Kingdome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſemblie, conſidering how greevous ſinne agaynſt GOD, and ſcandall to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, it were, for anie of this Kirk and kingdome, to joyne, or comply with the Sectarian enemie who having moſt injuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103550:10"/>and perfidiouſlie invaded this kingdome, have ſhed ſo much of the blood of GODS people, are deſtroying the Land, and are ſo wicked enemies to the Trueth of GOD, and work of Reformation; And having heard that ſome alreadie have fallen into theſe ſinnes: Therefore, the Commiſſion, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving ſo greevous ſcandall, Ordayne, that all ſuch as have, or ſhall joyne in Armes, or counſell, with the foreſayd enemie, upon the cleare notice and evidence thereof, ſhall be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and all ſuch as ſhall be found to have procured pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections from the ſayd enemie, execute anie orders from them, or given them intelligence, or have ſpoken favourablie of them, and to the advantage of their cauſe; And all ſuch as ſhall be found in anie other way to comply with them, ſhall be cenſured, according to the degrees of their compliance, as others have been cenſured, who have complyed with other enemies of the Covenant, and Cauſe of GOD, and the Peace of this Kirk and kingdome: And to the effect all perſones may be warned to guard and keepe themſelves from being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or carried away by anie inducement, or tentation, into ſuch courſe. It is appoynted that this Act be read publicklie in all the Congregations of this Kirk.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
